Center for Inspired Teaching 'Real World History' Oral History Project 194
People's Archive, MLK Library
Center for Inspired Teaching 'Real World History' Oral History Project
2014-
People's Archive, MLK Library
Center for Inspired Teaching
194
27.1 Gigabytes DIG_0029
228 Files DIG_0029
Arrangement
Interviews are grouped by academic year.
Biographical / Historical
The Center for Inspired Teaching's Real World History (RWH) is a city-wide high school history course that gives students applied history experience and exposes them to public history work through the cultural heritage institutions of the D.C. region. Each fall RWH students learn about the Great Migration through reading The Warmth of Other Suns, by Isabel Wilkerson, and embark on a semester-long oral history project with a Washingtonian who came to D.C. as part of the Migration. Together students and their narrators record life history interviews about the experience of migrating from the Jim Crow South to the D.C. Region.
Custodial History
The collection was donated to the Library in 2020 by The Center for Inspired Teaching.
Content Description
Oral history interviews recorded by students in the Real World History class at Center for Inspired Teaching.
Related Materials
Collection 198: Max Peterson Oral History Project
Families; African Americans; Neighborhoods; Oral History; Migration, Internal; Black persons
- Series 1: 2014-2015 School Year
  - Sub-Series 1: Interviews, 2014
    - Donella Matthews interview, 2014-12-08; Matthews, Donella, 1937-2017; Matthews, Jay
      Biographical / Historical
      Mrs. Donella Matthews was born December 27, 1937, in Cuthbert, Georgia. She left her hometown in September of 1956 to attend Tennessee State University where she majored in business education. While at Tennessee State, Mrs. Mathews met her husband, John Edward Mathews, and the two married a year after they met. Mr. Matthews decided to relocate the family to the D.C. region after he got a job at the Annapolis Gazette, and they moved into their current home in Washington, D.C., in 1969. Mrs. Mathews became an educator, and she and her husband had one daughter. Mrs. Mathews passed away on January 7, 2017.
      Scope and Contents
      In this oral history interview, Donella Mathews, a long time D.C. resident, discusses her experiences moving from Cuthbert, Georgia, to Washington, D.C. She discusses her education, her decision to move to D.C., and her life in Washington.
    - Fannie Webb Taylor interview, 2014-11-16; Taylor, Fannie Webb, 1925-2017; Brown, Azaria
      Mrs. Fannie Webb Taylor was born in New Orleans, Louisiana, on March 29, 1925, and had four sisters. Though she had a close relationship with her father, he left New Orleans in search of employment and never returned. Her mother worked as a "special-occasion" cook for white people in New Orleans, and the family had a difficult time financially after her father left. As a teenager, Mrs. Taylor worked as a night switchboard operator at Flint-Goodridge Hospital of Dillard University and attended the YMCA School of Commerce. After passing the civil service clerk typists' examination, her mother finally allowed Mrs. Taylor to leave New Orleans and she moved to Washington, D.C., in 1943 just before her 18th birthday. She began working at the Pentagon immediately upon arrival and moved in with her cousin who was renting a room at 800 P Street NW. While working as a clerk typist Mrs. Taylor married her husband, Vernon Robert Taylor, a civil engineering student at Howard University, and she left her job when he sponsored her through D.C. Teacher's College where she majored in English and History. After she and her husband had their second child, Mrs. Taylor began her teaching career at Benjamin Banneker Junior High School. She also received a Master of Arts in Teaching and a Certificate of Advanced Graduate Studies from Howard University. Mrs. Taylor was an active community member and a part of Zeta Phi Beta Sorority, National Council of Negro Women, Asbury United Methodist Church, and the Rollingcrest Senior Center. Mrs. Taylor passed away on December 18, 2017.
      In this oral history interview, Fannie Webb Taylor, a long time D.C. resident, discusses her experiences moving from New Orleans, Louisiana, to Washington, D.C.. She recalls her background in New Orleans and her reasons for moving north, as well as her journey to D.C. She also discusses how she established herself in the city, her work for the government, her personal life in Washington, and how she became a teacher at Banneker Junior High School.
    - Reverend Irene Pierce interview part 1, 2014-11-16; Pierce, Irene, Reverend, 1926-; Crumlin, Tenee'
      Rev. Irene Pierce was born on August 28, 1926, in Pickens, South Carolina. Rev. Pierce's father was killed shortly after she was born, and she and her two older siblings were raised by her mother, grandparents, and extended family. At age eight, Rev. Pierce came to Washington to live with her aunt and uncle. After graduating from Cardozo High School in 1943, she began a forty-year career with the Federal Government. During her time in the government, Rev. Pierce worked for the Department of Treasury, the National Production Authority, and the Department of Commerce. Rev. Pierce grew up attending both a Baptist and a Methodist church and comes from a long line of Methodist ministers. She began attending Asbury Methodist Church in 1945 and, after retiring from the government, went into the ministry and became a pastor in 1993. After pastoring her own church, she returned to Asbury as an Assistant Pastor. Rev. Pierce has a daughter, two granddaughters, and one great-granddaughter.
      In this oral history interview, Rev. Irene Pierce, a long time D.C. resident, discusses her experiences moving from Pickens, South Carolina, to Washington, D.C. She reflects on her family life and upbringing in Pickens, her move to D.C. at age eight, and her educational experiences in Washington. Rev. Pierce also discusses her career in government as well as her church life and work in the ministry.
    - Reverend Irene Pierce interview part 2, 2014-12-11; Pierce, Irene, Reverend, 1926-; Daniels, Devin
  - Sub-Series 2: Indexes, 2014
    - Fannie Webb Taylor index, 2014-11-16; Taylor, Fannie Webb, 1925-2017; Brown, Azaria
    - Reverend Irene Pierce index, 2014-11-16; Pierce, Irene, Reverend, 1926-; Crumlin, Tenee'
  - Sub-Series 3: Transcripts, 2014
    - Donella Matthews transcript, 2014-12-08; Matthews, Donella, 1937-2017; Matthews, Jay
    - Fannie Webb Taylor transcript part 1, 2014-11-16; Taylor, Fannie Webb, 1925-2017; Brown, Azaria
    - Fannie Webb Taylor transcript part 2, 2014-12-11; Taylor, Fannie Webb, 1925-2017; Lee, Kelly
    - Reverend Irene Pierce transcript part 1, 2014-11-16; Pierce, Irene, Reverend, 1926-; Crumlin, Tenee'
    - Reverend Irene Pierce transcript part 2, 2014-12-11; Pierce, Irene, Reverend, 1926-
      Daniels, Devin
  - Sub-Series 4: Images, 2014
    - Fannie Webb Taylor and Kelly Lee, 2014-12-11
      Interviewee Fannie Webb Taylor with her interviewer Kelly Lee at the The Phillips Collection. Lee was a high school student from Phelps A.C.E. high school enrolled in the Real World History Class.
      Taylor, Fannie Webb, 1925-2017; Lee, Kelly
    - Taylor Family, 2014-12-11
      Taylor family at The Phillips Collection.
    - Reverend Irene Pierce and Devin Daniels, 2014-12-11
      Interviewee Reverend Irene Pierce with her interviewer Devin Daniels at the The Phillips Collection. Daniels was a high school student from Dunbar high school enrolled in the Real World History Class.
      Pierce, Irene, Reverend, 1926-; Daniels, Devin
- Series 2: 2015-2016 School Year
  - Sub-Series 1: Interviews, 2015-2016
    - Bernard Hayes interview, 2015-12-18; rwhc_ohp_2015_009.wav; Hayes, H. Bernard, 1953-; Hassan, Ahmad
      Born in 1953, Bernard Hayes grew up in Georgia with his parents, Hubert Eugene Hayes and Ida Mae (Davis) Hayes, and six siblings. Hayes and his family moved in with an aunt in 1959 when his father migrated north alone to New York City. A year later, in 1960, after his father had secured a job and housing, the whole family moved to New York. Hayes would attend public school in New York and graduate from City College of New York where he studied journalism. In 1981, Hayes married his wife, Carol Ann Hayes, and in 1986, they moved to Washington, D.C. Hayes has had a successful career in radio journalism and currently works at Voice of America.
      In this oral history interview, Mr. Bernard Hayes discusses his life and experiences moving from Atlanta, Georgia, to New York City, and ultimately to Washington, D.C. Mr. Hayes discusses his early life in the South, his family's move to New York in 1960, and their transition into city life in the North. Mr. Hayes also discusses how the North provided him and his siblings more opportunities and the influence of his parents and other mentors on his life. Finally, Mr. Hayes discusses his move to Washington, D.C., in the 1980s to work at Voice of America.
      Migration, Internal; Black persons; African Americans
    - Caesar Dudley interview, 2015-12-18; Dudley, Caesar, -2018; Bayliss, Michael
      Caesar Dudley was born in Sandersville, Georgia, and was his parents' only child. His father was a farmer, and his mother was a domestic worker. When Mr. Dudley graduated from high school in 1941 (the Black high school in Sandersville did not go beyond the 11th grade), his parents send him to live with relatives in Washington, D.C., where he studied accounting and business at Cortez Peters Business College. Mr. Dudley then joined the military and served in the Army for three years (1943-1946). While in the Army, he served overseas and visited places such as France, Germany, the Mediterranean, Japan, and Korea. Upon returning to the U.S., Mr. Dudley continued his education with the help of the G.I. Bill. He also married in 1949 and had two sons. He then worked for eighteen years at the Department of the Army and another seventeen years as a courtroom deputy clerk for the U.S. District Court. Mr. Dudley retired in the 1980s, and passed away in 2018.
      In this oral history interview, Caesar Dudley, a long time D.C. resident, discusses his experiences moving from Sandersville, Georgia, to Washington, D.C. He discusses his upbringing in Sandersville, his reasons for moving north, and the cultural differences between where he grew up and D.C. He also reflects on Sandersville, the South, and the cultural shifts that took place in the District over decades.
    - Damita Jo Goldsmith interview, 2016-02-01; Goldsmith, Damita Jo, 1951-; Akhigbe, Rebecca
      Damita Jo Goldsmith was born July 29, 1951, in Dennison, Texas, the oldest of her parents' five children. Since her father was in the Air Force, she moved to Guam with her family at age seven. After living in Guam for two years, the family relocated again to the Philippines for another two-year period. Ms. Goldsmith and her family returned to the U.S. in 1962, and the family migrated to the D.C. region after a month's stay with her father's family in Louisiana. After living in the District for a year and attending J. C. Nalle Elementary School, Ms. Goldsmith and her family moved to Chapel Oaks, Maryland. After a few years in Chapel Oaks, they moved to Capitol Heights, Maryland, and she graduated from Fairmont Heights High School the year before integration in that area, 1969. Ms. Goldsmith went on to attend Morgan State University where she met her husband and graduated in 1973. The two married a few years after graduation and had two sons. Ms. Goldsmith began her career at UPS as a part-time clerk in 1979 and later joined the management team. She retired in 2007 and has worked as the senior activity coordinator at the Glenarden Community Rec Center since then.
      In this oral history interview Damita Jo Goldsmith discusses her life and experiences settling in the Washington, D.C., region as a child. She discusses her upbringing in a military family, her family's move from Louisiana to Washington, her educational experiences in the D.C. region, her career at UPS, and her post-retirement work at the Glenarden Community Rec Center.
    - Eleanor Kelly interview, 2015-12-01; Kelly, Eleanor; Branch, Maya
      Eleanor Kelly was born in Blaney, South Carolina. Though her parents were sharecroppers when she was born, the family did well and they bought their own land and built a house by the time she was a teenager. Before finishing high school, Mrs. Kelly moved to Washington, D.C., with her Aunt Rebecca and enrolled in Cortez Peters Business College. Mrs. Kelly later moved in with her sister Alberta and her family, and they moved to New York when her brother-in-law was stationed in Staten Island. Mrs. Kelly returned to Washington to live with another sister after Alberta's husband was stationed overseas. After returning to Washington, she worked at WTOP for several years before working for the government. After marrying her husband, Moses Kelly, Mrs. Kelly moved all around the country due to Mr. Kelly's work for the Secret Service. She and her husband had one daughter, Doris. After Mr. Kelly's retirement, Mrs. Kelly and her husband moved back to Blythewood, South Carolina, to live in her family's home.
      In this oral history interview, Eleanor Kelly, a long time D.C. resident, discusses her experiences moving from Blythewood, South Carolina, to Washington, D.C. She recalls her early life in both Blaney and Blythewood, South Carolina, and her move to Washington when she was in high school. Mrs. Kelly discusses her early years in D.C., moving to Staten Island with her sister and brother-in-law, as well as her return to Washington. She also talks about moving to California with her husband later in her life.
    - Henry Breedlove interview, 2016-01-01; Breedlove, Henry, 1939-; Jones, Mattie
      Born in Vienna, Georgia, in 1939, Henry Breedlove was born to a large family with 10 siblings. His parents worked as sharecroppers and Mr. Breedlove and his siblings worked with them. At 18 his parents sent him to live with in his sister in Washington, D.C. He quickly got a construction job working and remained in the industry for his entire career. He lived with his sister until 1971 when he married his wife and got his own place. In 1999 they moved to Temple Hills, Maryland. He and his wife had one son who passed away in 2013.
      In this oral history interview, Henry Breedlove, a long time D.C. resident, discusses his experiences moving from Vienna, Georgia, to Washington, D.C. He talks about his upbringing in Vienna as well as how his parents sent him to live in Washington when he was 18 years old (in 1957) since they feared for his life after a confrontation he had with some white people. Mr. Breedlove also discusses his career in construction, his relationship with his wife, the passing of their son in 2013, and the role of religion in his life.
    - Julius Watson interview, 2016-04-06; Watson, Julius; Thomas, Isaiah
      Born and raised in South Carolina, Julius Watson was the oldest of his parents' children and grew up in a small, two-bedroom house with his sister, mother, grandmother, two aunts, and three cousins. Being in the Navy, his father was not around during his upbringing. Mr. Watson was a good athlete as a young man and played football in high school. After being arrested and jailed for three days for a crime he didn't commit, Mr. Watson moved to Washington, D.C., in 1968 to live with his grandmother for a short time. He then moved to Connecticut to live with his father who was working at Wesleyan University. While living with his father Mr. Watson received a scholarship to play football at Wesleyan. They then moved to St. Thomas before Mr. Watson returned to Washington, D.C. He went on to get married and have three children with his wife before the two got a divorced. Today he is a grandfather and likes to take his grandkids out fishing, among other excursions.
      In this oral history interview, Julius Watson, a long time D.C. resident, discusses his experiences moving from South Carolina to Washington, D.C. He talks about cultural differences he sees between the South and D.C., his marriage, and his relationships with his children and grandchildren. He also discusses his upbringing in South Carolina, his love of sports, race relations in the South, time spent living in Connecticut and St. Thomas, and his love of music. He also reflects on the decision to leave South Carolina as well as the lessons he has learned after living in the city for over 45 years.
    - Kathy Elaine Senior interview, 2016-01-16; Senior, Kathy Elaine, 1941-; Yadeto, Jabesso
      Kathy Elaine Senior was born on April 17, 1941, in Columbus, Georgia. She grew up with her parents, Dennis and Maggie Senior, as well as her younger brother, Dennis Senior, Jr. Ms. Senior's mother was a registered nurse at the Columbus City Hospital for thirty years and met her husband there when she was a student nurse. Following in her mother's footsteps, Ms. Senior moved to Washington to attend Freedmen's Hospital School of Nursing in 1959 and graduated in 1962. She then had a 48-year career as a registered nurse (27 years at St. Elizabeths Hospital and 21 years as a self-employed nurse). Since retiring from nursing, Ms. Senior has worked with her brother on a business venture called 5Linx Incorporated. Ms. Senior loves to travel internationally and is passionate about social justice causes.
      In this oral history interview, Kathy Elaine Senior, a long time D.C. resident, discusses her experiences moving from Columbus, Georgia, to Washington, D.C. She reflects on her upbringing in Columbus, race relations in the city during her childhood, and reasons she moved to Washington. She also talks about her time at Freedmen's Hospital School of Nursing, her career at St. Elizabeths Hospital, and her activism in Washington.
    - Korea Stowder interview, 2015-12; Strowder, Korea Clark, 1920-2018; Rich, Jamilya
      Korea Clark Strowder was born on March 14, 1920, in Denver, Colorado, the youngest of her four siblings. Her mother died when she was only three, and her father moved the family to a farm just outside of the city. Struggling to take care of four children, Ms. Strowder's father sent her to live with an aunt in Des Moines, Iowa, but she soon returned to Denver since her aunt had many children of her own. A few years later, her father passed away unexpectedly and Ms. Strowder and her siblings were sent to live with different relatives. She lived with an aunt in St. Joseph, Missouri, but she saved up her money to leave after graduating from high school due to the intense racism and discrimination in St. Joseph. Ms. Strowder moved to Omaha, Nebraska, where a sister lived to attend beauty school before coming to Washington, D.C., in 1943. After arriving in D.C., Ms. Strowder worked in different government offices until she and her husband, Joseph Strowder, had children, at which point she began working in the home. Ms. Strowder later came to work in education and served as a pupil personnel aide at Bundy Elementary School from 1963 to 1971. At age 51, Ms. Strowder began studying mass communications at the University of the District of Columbia (UDC) and became a librarian. In 1979 she retired as head librarian of the Sursum Corda Community Library. Ms. Strowder passed away March 27, 2018.
      In this oral history interview, Korea Strowder, a long time D.C. resident, discusses her life and experiences moving from Denver, Colorado, to Washington, D.C. She talks about her family history in Kentucky, her upbringing in Denver, as well as her experiences living in St. Joseph, Missouri, after her father died and she and her siblings were sent to live with different relatives. Ms. Strowder recalls a spectacle lynching that took place in St. Joseph, and discusses experiences with racism and discrimination in the different places she lived. She also discusses her life, education, and career in Washington; including growing up the descendants of enslaved people, The Great Depression, and World World II.
    - Louise Baxter interview, 2016-01-07; Baxter, Louise; Aguilar, Kenya
      Louise Baxter was born in Jalapa, South Carolina, but she moved into nearby Newberry, South Carolina, when she was still young. Ms. Baxter was an only child and was raised by her grandparents after her mother moved to Washington in search of better economic opportunities. Her mother would send money back to the family, and starting in her early teens, Ms. Baxter would visit her mother in D.C. during the summers. After graduating from high school, Ms. Baxter's grandmother died and she moved to Washington to live with her mother. Once in Washington, she began a 35-year career in custodial work (20 years at the CIA building and 15 years at Georgetown University). Ms. Baxter had two children, a boy and a girl.
      In this oral history interview, Louise Baxter, a long time D.C. resident, discusses her life and experiences moving from Newberry, South Carolina, to Washington, D.C. She reflects on her upbringing in Newberry, moving to Washington at the age of 17, experiences with discrimination in Washington, and her career working in the Central Intelligence Agency (CIA) building as well as at Georgetown University.
    - Mabel Mitchell interview, 2016-01-08; rwhc_ohp_2015_010.wav; Mitchell, Mabel; Eigsti, Allison
      Born in the early 1940s, Ms. Mabel Mitchell grew up in Raleigh, North Carolina. When Ms. Mitchell was only three years old her father died, leaving her mother to raise her with the help of grandparents and extended family. Though Ms. Mitchell was her parents' only child, she was raised with a cousin who was like a sister. After graduating from high school, Ms. Mitchell moved to Washington, DC, in search of work and lived with her aunt. After working a variety of jobs, Ms. Mitchell secured a job at the Bureau of Navy Personnel beginning a forty-one-year career in the government. Ms. Mitchell retired in 2010.
      In this oral history interview, Ms. Mabel Mitchell, a long time DC resident, discusses her life and experiences moving from Raleigh, North Carolina, to Washington, DC. Ms. Mitchell discusses her early life in Raleigh, her move to Washington, DC, in the early 1950s, her transition to living and working in DC, and her long career in the government. Ms. Mitchell also talks about segregation and racial discrimination in Washington, as well as gentrification in the city in the 21st century.
      Migration, Internal; Women; Black persons; African Americans; Segregation; Gentrification; Discrimination
    - Shirley Debrow interview, 2016-01-02; rwhc_ohp_2015_011.wav; Debrow, Shirley, 1946-; Debrow, Samuel
      Born in 1946, Shirley M. Debrow grew up in North Carolina with her parents and two brothers. After graduating from high school in 1964, she moved to Philadelphia, PA, with an aunt. Ms. Debrow later moved to Washington, DC, in 1966, where she has lived ever since. In Washington, Ms. Debrow attended Federal City College (now UDC) and came under the mentorship of DC community activist, Kimi Gray. With the help of Gray, Ms. Debrow opened a daycare center and served as the center's director. She also worked on the campaigns of DC Mayor Marion Barry. Ms. Debrow began a long and successful career as a recreation specialist with the DC Department of Parks and Recreation in 1987, working most recently at the Volta Park Recreation Center in Georgetown. Ms. Debrow loves to travel, enjoys outdoor activities and lives an active and healthy lifestyle. She also had one son, Steven, who was born in 1968.